Replacing the authorization servlet

It is also possible to replace the authorization servlet in any version of OA4MP with a customized version. You may then, for instance, use LDAP or Shibboleth for authentication. The protocols require that your module occupy the authorize endpoint. The assumptions then are that

Your module will handle the authentication.
After a successful authentication, your module will make a callout to another, private endpoint.
This private endpoint is tasked to set up all the state and check that the request is valid. Skipping a call to this module means there will be no state for this request and all subsequent attempts to use the service will be rejected.
This private endpoint is either protected at the network level (access via Apache) or with a security constraint in Tomcat (Tomcat only servers).
Your call to this will follow a mini-protocol, then process the response. Each version of OA4MP has its own details on this.

Having Tomcat handle security.

If you have a Tomcat only service, then you must protect this endpoint. A typical security security constraint is the following, which should be added to the deployment descriptor (web.xml file)

    <security-constraint>
           <web-resource-collection>
               <web-resource-name>Lockdown_initiate_endpoint</web-resource-name>
               <url-pattern>/authorized</url-pattern>
               <http-method>GET</http-method>
               <http-method>POST</http-method>
               <http-method>PUT</http-method>
               <http-method>DELETE</http-method>
           </web-resource-collection>
           <auth-constraint/>
       </security-constraint>

which will prevent all access to the authorized endpoint except from Tomcat itself. If you access the service from Apache, you will have to limit access to this endpoint at the server level to calls from localhost only. The authorized servlet comes with this security constraint enabled by default since it is better to have the authentication fail if there is any question about the setup.

Accessing the Authorized Servlet for OA4MP under OAuth 1.0a

The initial setup

Since OA4MP is no longer authorizing the login (e.g. Shibboleth is), you need to deploy the correct servlet in your web.xml file, to wit AuthorizedServlet. So a typical entry would look like

<servlet>
       <servlet-name>authorized</servlet-name>
       <servlet-class>edu.uiuc.ncsa.myproxy.oa4mp.server.servlet.AuthorizedServlet</servlet-class>
       <load-on-startup>0</load-on-startup>
   </servlet>
   <servlet-mapping>
       <servlet-name>authorized</servlet-name>
       <url-pattern>/authorized</url-pattern>
   </servlet-mapping>

NOTE that the endpoint is authorized for here. See below for more details on accessing this. In effect, to be spec. compliant, a mini-API is implemented for this which will now be explained.

The mini-protocol

The specification requires that the call to your module has the oauth_token present, which you must pass on to the authorized servlet -- this the internal identifier linking the user to their request. A common method of deployment, e.g for Shibboleth, is to use Apache with ProxyPass for Tomcat and only allow localhost access to Tomcat. Your module can then call Tomcat. The expected request to the server consists of 4 parameters:

username the username that the user authenticates with
password the password used
lifetime the certificate lifetime (in milliseconds)
oauth_token the token generated in the initial request by the server

A typical example invocation would be

localhost://oa4mp.bigstate.edu:8080/authorized?oauth_token=sj38GHTYf24354&username=bob&password=somepassword&lifetime=100000000

Assuming that your oa4mp instance is deployed at oa4mp.bigstate.edu. It is assumed that all parameters will be url escaped. The response contains two items

status a code, "ok" indicating success
redirect_uri which is the redirect generated by OA4MP. This should be used to redirect the user's browser and is, if you recall, generated from information only OA4MP has in the client's initial request.

For instance the body of the response contains the following two lines to parse:

status=ok
redirect_uri=https%3A%2F%2Fportal.example.edu%2Foauth%2Fready%3Foauth_token%3Dhdk48Djdsa%26oauth_verifier%3Dhfdp7dh39dks9884

If there is an error, then the first line will not have a status of "ok" and an error should be issued by your module. (Don't forget to check the OA4MP logs to find why it failed!)

Accessing the Authorized Servlet for OA4MP under OAuth 2.0

Initial setup

The servlet used in this case is named OA2AuthorizedServlet. So a typical entry would look like

  <servlet>
      <servlet-name>authorized</servlet-name>
      <servlet-class>edu.uiuc.ncsa.myproxy.oa4mp.oauth2.servlet.OA2AuthorizedServlet</servlet-class>
  </servlet>
  <servlet-mapping>
      <servlet-name>authorized</servlet-name>
      <url-pattern>/authorized</url-pattern>
  </servlet-mapping>

Note that the name of this servlet may be altered without changing the protocol. Some installation prefer to call it /init since authorize and authorized are very similar.

The mini-protocol

The very first step in the OAuth 2.0 protocol is that the user goes to the authorize endpoint which will then simply call the end authorized endpoint by passing along verbatim the original request your authorization module received. For instance, if your server got the following request

https://your.server.edu/oauth2/authorize?state=s0jByyFvSNeoDUZ1GbyRy&nonce=ABC75344A&...

You do the authorization and once completed successfully, you call the authorized servlet:

https://localhost/oauth2/authorized?state=s0jByyFvSNeoDUZ1GbyRy&nonce=ABC75344A&...

All state and error checking will be done for you. You will simply receive the standard response (with HTML status code of 200, since 302 is reserved for error conditions -- see below for more) in JSON of the token and the state (if that was passed in the initial request) -- simply pass this response back to the client in the standard OIDC redirect. For instance

    {"code":"urn:oauth2:aMQ53UmEtb5cM6WF/ps7wOmYQoJTTKAW9","state":"s0jByyFvSNeoDUZ1GbyRy"}

Errors

The authorized servlet supports all of the same error codes as the standard OAuth 2.0/OIDC specification. This means that there will be an HTML status code of 302 (a redirect) to the callback url that the client supplied (in the request and at registration). This may again be passed along directly to the client which is required to process it. For example, if the above request were invalid and had consequently, failed then if the base url of the error is https://your.client.org/cb your authorize module would get the following redirect, as per the OA4MP/OIDC spec:

    Location: https://your.client.org/cb?
      error=invalid_request
      &error_description=
        the%20request%20is%20not%20valid%20or%20malformed
      &state=s0jByyFvSNeoDUZ1GbyRy

Changes to the OA4MP server by version.

3.4

OAUTH-203: Clients may request supported scopes at registration time.
OAUTH-212: PEM encodings broken by change to Apache base 64 codec.
OAUTH-213: Make TLS version configurable in the SSL configuration.
OAUTH-217: Added discovery, in a server/.well-known/openid_configuration.
CIL-339: EPTID mismatch handled as a separate case.
CIL-344: Client management API created. Sample scripts created as well.
CIL-356: Clients may have individual LDAP configurations.
CIL-359: ID tokens must be signed.
CIL-371: added claim for cert_subject_dn to be returned for the org.cilogon.userinfo scope.
CIL-378: Clients with same creation timestamp are not all displayed in CLI.
CIL-388: Server wars now include more meta information in the META-INF/MANIFEST.MF file about the build.
Java object serialization issue: Updated dependencies on Apache commons-collections to 3.2.2.
Removed legacy unused Java object serialization from backend file store.

3.4 Release notes

Note that in this release of OA4MP there are two new tables that are required if the server uses SQL -based storage. One for admin clients and another for permissions. If the user (i.e., as defined in the configuration file that accesses the data) has create permission in the database, then the tables will be automatically created. If not, then you must create them manually using one of the scripts found here.

You must also create signing keys for OIDC. This is done with the command line tool

3.3

CIL-252: Scope handler which queries LDAP for user attributes.
CIL-264: Document examples using the cURL command.
CIL-268: Added sample OA4MP OIDC configuration to web documentation.
CIL-273: LDAP support for OA4MP.
CIL-286: Failed client registration not cleaned up.
CIL-299: "Max retries exceeded" message from MariaDB connection pool. This was because the method in question was only partially synchronized.
CIL-309: Refresh token fixes and improvements.
CIL-312: Null pointer exception when parsing URIs. The built-in parser for URIs is rather stupid in certain cases and would throw an NPE when parsing. This is now being handled better to prevent this.
CIL-317: exception setting transaction state if use waits to finish exchange until after initial grant has expired and garbage collected.
CIL-319: Indicate in DN if the user is from and InCommon or eduGain IDP.
CIL-320: DB Service fix to get information to resolve CIL-319.
CIL-324: Attempting to send many email notifications at once causes failures.
OAUTH-189: Invalid nonce causes reloadof authorization page to fail.
OAUTH-191: Defer connecting to MyProxy until the getCert call, if possible.
OAUTH-194: OIDC token endpoint should return error with status of 400.
OAUTH-196: Documentation needs updating after file name change internally.
OAUTH-197: Testing from the command line documentation shows sending the secret to the authorization endpoint, which is not in the specification.
OAUTH-198: Pass teh HTTPServletRequest to the basic scope handler. This allows implementors more flexibility.
OAUTH-199: Pass HttpServlet request to custom scope handlers.
OAUTH-200: Connection pooling does not clean out stale connections.
OAUTH-201: Username incorrectly flagged as the primary key for the asset table, causing and error on updates.
OAUTH-202: Tomcat 6 is not supported for this release of OA4MP. You must have at least version 7 or higher.
OAUTH-206: Refresh token lifetime limited. A logic bug made the lifetime of refresh tokens decrease on refresh, eventually yielding invalid refresh tokens. All refresh tokens now are valid for the full requested time.
OAUTH-208: Remove dependeny on one-jar plug in for building executable jars, since it is no longer supported.
OAUTH-209: Remove dependency on Google Code's maven repository.
Added new command line client for testing purposes.

3.2.1

CIL-101: (reopened with an additional parameter for the overloaded myproxy username)
CIL-210: Return CILogon specific claims fromthe getUserInfo endpoint.
CIL-211: New attributes for the user, affiliation, display name and organizational unit.
CIL-227: Refresh token lifetimes should be ignored if not enabled on the server.
CIL-231: EPPN and EPTID no longer omitted from X509v3 extension.
CIL-234: Fermi National Lab specific distinguished names, along with a configuration option for the server to disable generation of these.
CIL-240: update for items from command line not working.
CIL-257: Unwanted serial string changes on user updates
CIL-258: Allow OGS CA to omit versio number from certification requests since MyProxy accepts these.
CIL-260: Allow for restoring archived users from command line.
OAUTH-184:Additional claims returned from the getToken endpoint.
OAUTH-192: Enabling use of the remote user header from an external authorization module could allow a user to change their name.
OAUTH-193: Empty responses to cert request.

3.2

OAUTH-181: Updated server walkthrough.
OAUTH-183: Update documentation for using remote user.
OAUTH-184: Plugin capability for additional IODC claims.
OAUTH-185: Support for custom scopes and additional claims.
OAUTH-188: Fixed broken links in the getting-started page.
CIL-194: Searching for MyProxy servers in CILogon now uses standard OA4MP libraries.
CIL-196: ServerDN option in configuration now can be over-ridden in the MyProxy tag.
CIL-197: Propagating MyProxy changes to CILogon.
Added PKCS 7 encoding support to the certificate utility

3.1.1

OAUTH-180: Support OIDC servers that do not use a nonce.
CIL-101: Add setTransaction state call.
CIL-136: Documenting the OAuth 2.0 authorized servlet.
CIL-141: Improve pinging servers
CIL-170, CIL-171: Missing log4j properties restored.
CIL-172: Multiple LIGO IdPs supported.
CIL-173: Fix handling of incorrect password.

3.1.0

CIL-194: CILogon server only returns cert from last Myproxy server
CIL-196: server DN override in myproxy configuration not read.

3.1

OAUTH-179: Updated apache http client libraries to 4.4.1 since previous version had an SSL server hostname validation vulnerability:
CIL-169: Mail notifications failing.

3.0

Java 8 support: Due to internal changes to Java, this release requires Java 8 and will not work with previous versions of Java.
OAUTH-164: Support for id_tokens in OAuth 2 module
OAUTH-165: Passing the skin parameter in with the initial request.
OAUTH-168: Making OA4MP for OAuth 2.0 spec. compliant.
OAUTH-169: Removed "error url" from the OAuth 2 registration page
OAUTH-170: Typo in online documentation. Examples had tags corrected to <service>
OAUTH-171: MyProxy Logon now supports setting the socket timeout.
OAUTH-172: Expose MyProxy socket timeout in OA4MP configuration.
OAUTH-173: Improved error message on session timeout.
OAUTH-174: Error handling in OAuth 2 component.
OAUTH-175: Possible concurrency issue with MariaDB connections.
OAUTH-176: Specify DN (distinguished name) for MyProxy server(s).
OAUTH-177: Documentation for the new server DN option.

1.3

OAUTH-162: Client secret must be sent on access token request but not on authorization request.
OAUTH-163: State must be returned in OAuth 2 component with authorization response callback.

1.2.1

OAUTH-127: MyProxyLogon website updated to point to current release.
OAUTH-129: Sorting entries with the the CLI ls command. Before there was no sorting, now it is done by client ID or date, where applicable.
OAUTH-134: Updating documentation on how to run a monitor.
OAUTH-154: Removed possible redundant/conflicting maven dependencies.
OAUTH-156: Turn off default logging for MyProxyLogon. This permits use of the MyProxyLogon module as a library without getting logging messages to the console (the previous default).
OAUTH-157: Client registration page not saving client secret under OAuth 1.0a protocol.
OAUTH-158: Updated links on generic client registration page to current documentation.
OAUTH-159: Update documentation for this release.
OAUTH-160: Regularize and improve version reporting at component (CLI, client, server) startup.

1.2

OAUTH-131: Improved client registration for OAuth 2 servers.
OAUTH-149: Remove support for MyProxyLogon to use SSL version 3. (This mitigates the POODLE attack.)
OAUTH-152: Do not show detailed MyProxy error message if authorization fails.
OAUTH-153: Improved logging for MyProxy errors and successes.
OAUTH-155: Updated documentation to explain new OAuth 2 client registration process.

1.1.3

OAUTH-139: CLI might return an incorrect list of items after several updates.
OAUTH-140: MyProxy component didn't quite log completely to the configured log file.
OAUTH-141: Improved client/server walkthough. This is documentation that permits an administrator to deploy both a client and server locally with a self-signed cert for testing purposes.
OAUTH-143: Enabling the Globus DN option should have had better documentation pointing at the server requirements for JGlobus.
OAUTH-144: Jetty version was incorrect, causing certain build issues. This was standardized on version 6.1.26 to ensure consistent builds.
OAUTH-147: Potential cleanup thread failure with a filestore. If a filestore is used and one of the files is corrupted (e.g. due to a system crash at the time of writing it) then the cleanup thread would fail to start. Now such corrupted files are simply logged in catalina.out and ignored otherwise.
OAUTH-148: Maria DB support added.

1.1.2

OAUTH-112: Servlet initialization is injected now, decoupling it more from Tomcat startup.
OAUTH-113: MyProxy does not handle PAM challenges. The documentation has been updated with a link to the appropriate page on the MyProxy website where this is discussed.
OAUTH-117: Server install walkthrough updated and improved to reflect changes (in particular, it now makes us of the resolution of OAUTH-110).
OAUTH-118. Build error in maven caused OAuth2 command line tools to issue an NPE in certain cases.
OAUTH-119: Loading objects into the CLI that do not have identifiers caused an NPE. This could only arise really if someone directly edited an entry in a text editor (e.g. if the installation was backed by a filestore). In that case it would not be possible to load any objects from that store into the CLI, preventing editing of them.
OAUTH-120: The new -component flag allows an administrator to start the CLI with the named component as an argument. E.g. rather than start the CLI and use the approval component, just issue
./oa4mp-cli -component approvals

OAUTH-125: "About" and "Overview" links on website were broken.
OAUTH-126: Website now lists the version number with the "latest" link.
OAUTH-130: Documentation amended to clarify which version of OA4MP (based on OAuth 1.0a or OAuth 2.0) to use.
OAUTH-133: Configuration option to convert standard DN to (legacy) Globus identifiers. This is mostly useful for installations that have been using Globus for a very long time.
OAUTH-135: Failure in authentication were not displaying the correct message. They should route the user back to the login page for another attempt.

1.1.1

OAUTH-105:Added support for file includes to configuration files.
OAUTH-105: Added checks to prevent cycles in aliases and files
OAUTH-106: Adding fully qualified host name to client approval notifications.

1.1

OAUTH-47 Now supports building with maven 3.0+ There was an issue with earlier an pom version that prevented this.
Support for OAuth 2 protocol. This includes full server and client support as well as various supported stores (mysql, postgres, files) and admin tools.
OAUTH-94: Fix for passthrough of Shibboleth attributes. A username transformation interface has been created. This will be invoked immediately before the call to MyProxy. Users that wish to customize this may do so by implementing the interface and setting it in the environment at server startup.
OAUTH-96: Check for a bad PKCS10 CSR (missing version number which must be set to 0) created by pyOpenSSL is now in place and an informative message is now issued. Earlier the Bouncy Castle code allowed for this, Sun does not.
OAUTH-99: Old documentation at Science Gateway Security site removed. Everything is redirected to this site now.
OAUTH-102: No username returned with cert in certain cases. Fixed.

1.0.7

Added support to make using log 4j optional. It had been disabled which interfered with some installations.
Fixed bug OAUTH-90.
Fixed bug OAUTH-94. This adds a configuration option to return the DN of the user's cert as the username.
All new command line tools that allow for managing clients and approvals.
Changed client index page to be more up to date.
Removed all explicit references to Bouncy Castle. This should prevent future jar pollution from incompatible versions. JGlobus still uses this though....

Set mysql and postgres jars to be provided rather than included in the release so that projects that need only a single type of storage are not required to install both of these.

1.0.6

Version number is now printed to the console whenever the server starts up.
Support for authentication using the REMOTE_USER (or any other) header.
Improved error handling on the server, especially in cases where the MyProxyLogon client encounters a runtime exception.
OAUTH-80: errors resulting from JGlobus broken build will be resolved by their conforming to standard maven practices
Fix for OAUTH-83 documentation error in configuring mail addresses
OAUTH-84 failure to return a complete certificate chain from MyProxy in a certain case
OAUTH-85 failure to configure logging could result in an error. Default is to dump everything into the tomcat logs.
Use of new JGlobus release 2.0.5.
Bouncy Castle version set to 1.43 to support JGlobus release 2.0.5.
Added signatures for the lastest downloadable war.

1.0.5

Support for limited proxy generation. Allows the server to generate a public/private keypair and issue a limited proxy. The result is a certificate chain.
Deny HTTP header. This sets the HTTP header to "deny" which prevents clickjacking attacks.
Added logging support. Standard Java logging is now available and configurable.
Default MyProxy server on localhost. If no MyProxy server is specified, one is assumed to be running on localhost.
Improved admin tools. In particular, improved the CLI to give more readable messages.
Improved SQL install scripts.
Links in the documentation to the latest versions of these scripts.
More and better documentation.

Command line tools for OA4MP

These are a set of programs that are accessible from a CLI (command line interface) allow an administrator to do CRUD (Create, Read, Update and Delete) operations on client records and approvals. There is also the option to copy a store completely from one store to another.

Getting the tools

OAuth 1.0a

The latest version of the Oauth 1.0a command line tool is available at oa4mp-cli.jar You should also get the script that runs this too, oa4mp-cli

Oauth 2.0

The latest version of the Oauth 2.0 command line tool is available at oa2-cli.jar You should also get the script that runs this too, oa2-cli

Configuration

The tool uses a standard configuration file exactly like the server. Indeed, you can just point the tool at the server configuration file. You will need to supply the name of the configuration in the file you want to use. Aliases can be quite handy here. Given the abilities of the CLI to do quick copies of the store, it pays to have a backup (file) store configured and occasionally simple copy the active store to that. There are many possible uses. It is assumed that the tools are installed in a location called $OA4MP_HOME. Normally the default for this is

OAuth 1.0a: OA4MP_HOME=/opt/oa4mp

OAuth 2.0: OA4MP_HOME=opt/oa2 Note that we will be discussing the OA4MP tools rather than the OA2 tools in what follows. Everything here works the same if you replace oa4mp-* by oa2-*

The assumption of the script is that files are in the following directory structure

$OA4MP_HOME/etc/admin-cfg.xml - the configuration file
$OA4MP_HOME/lib/oa4mp-cli.jar - the jar containing the CLI
$OA4MP_HOME/bin/oa4mp-cli - the script for running this. Be sure it is set to be executable.

The default name of the configuration is assumed to be "default" (no quotes). If you invoke the script with no arguments it will use this and the above configuration file.

Running the CLI

Invocation from the command line is usually done with the supplied shell script, oa4mp-cli. The invocation syntax is

oa4mp-cli [configName configFile]

You should run this as root and might need to set the script to be executable if it is not. If you give neither arguments then defaults are used. Invoke with the argument "--help" for more information. If you give one argument it is assumed to be the configuration name in the default configuration file.

Command line options for the jar.

You should run this from the script, but if you want or need to specify invoke the jar directly, the invocation options they are listed here.

Argument | Value required? | Required? | Description
-cfg | Y | Y | The full path to the configuration file.
-name | F | F | The name of the configuration within the file. If there is a single configuration in the file, then no name is needed. If there are multiple configurations you must specify which one to use.
-log | F | F | The full path log file. If this is not specified then a file named "log.xml" is dumped into the invocation directory.
-use | F | F | Specify the component to use. Rather than loading the whole CLI then use-ing a components (such as clients) you may simply specify that here.
-v | F | F | No argument. Turns on verbose logging so that much more information is dumped onto the console. This is useful for debugging or just if you want to see what it is up to.

    java -jar oa4mp-cli.jar -cfg /path/to/cfg.xml -name myConfig -log /path/to/mylog.xml -use approvals

This would load the configuration named "myConfig" from the given file, write the log to a file called "mylog.xml" and bring up the approvals component.

Running the tool

The CLI consists of utilities for each component that can be used. Once invoked you will see the startup banner and prompt:

[mybox bin]# ./oa4mp-cli
**********************************************************
* OA4MP CLI (Command Line Interpreter)                   *
* Version 3.4-SNAPSHOT                                   *
* By Jeff Gaynor  NCSA                                   *
*  (National Center for Supercomputing Applications)     *
*                                                        *
* type 'help' for a list of commands                     *
*      'exit' or 'quit' to end this session.             *
**********************************************************
oa4mp >

If you type "help" You will get

oa4mp >help

Here are the commands available:
use
load
To get more information on a command type

command --help

Basic supported commands are

use - specify a component to use.
load configName [configFile] - load the given named configuration from the current config file. Specify the config file if you need a different one.

To see the help for, say, the use command you would issue

 oa4mp> use --help

 Choose the component you wish to use.
 you specify the component as use + name. Supported components are
 clients - edit client records
 approvals - edit client approval records
 copy - copy an entire store.

 e.g.

 use clients

 will call up the client management component.
 Type 'exit' when you wish to exit the component and return to the main menu

Each of these components; clients, approvals and copy is described in detail below. But first, a few preliminary notions.

Index vs. Unique ID

Since most objects have unique identifiers, you can specify these are arguments at any time it makes sense to do so by prefixing the id with a forward slash, "/". If there is a list of objects, you can also specify the index on the list as the target of the operation. Most components have a command to list everything in the active component (the ls command).

After you issue an ls (no arguments) you will see a complete list of items in the store. These are numbered on the right hand side. This is the item's index. You may then specify the index directly. E.g. to print out a long version of the item with index 4 issue

ls 4

Typically you will know the unique identifier for an item and you can enter this if you escape it with a forward slash (/). To give the long listing of an object with unique identifier myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/a4b78549990 you would issue

ls /myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/a4b78549990

Note that since there is no canonical ordering of objects in a store, you should always issue an ls before using the index. It is generally always safer to use the unique identifier.

Options supported in each storage tool.

size - number of entries in the current component.
ls [index | /uniqueId] - list all items or the details of a given item
update [index | /uniqueId] - edit the item
rm [index | /uniqueId] - remove an entry
create [uniqueId] - create a new entry with the optional id.

Each of these in turn will be discussed in detail.

Common commands for all storage components.

Getting The Number Of Objects In a Component.

This will print the number of elements in the current storage component.
Example. For showing the number of clients in a store you would have something like the following

oa4mp >use clients
  clients >size
    Current store has 22 entries
  clients >exit
exiting ...
oa4mp >

Listing Object or Details of an Object.

This lists every element in the current component. The default is to sort by the given identifier. Clients are sorted by creation date. At this point, sorting behavior cannot be changed. Each record is recorded on a single line. No argument prints out everything in the store. Giving the optional index or unique identifier will print a detailed listing of the object.
Example. Listing a specific object by unique identifier

oa4mp >use approvals
  approvals >ls
  0. ClientApproval[approved=true, approver=null, id=myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/468afcd5f598227e1a0b79e6e94b3506, on Mon Apr 01 11:37:58 CDT 2013]
  1. ClientApproval[approved=true, approver=auto-approver, id=myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/1e4310262889ebdf72b8a7b148acdf2a, on Mon Jul 09 16:21:47 CDT 2012]
  approvals >

and now print out the details on number 1:

  approvals >ls 1

Approver:auto-approver
  Identifier:myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/1e4310262889ebdf72b8a7b148acdf2a
  Approved at:Mon Jul 09 16:21:47 CDT 2012
  Is approved? true
  approvals >

We could have done the exact same thing by simply using the unique identifier:

    approvals>ls /myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/1e4310262889ebdf72b8a7b148acdf2a

Approver:auto-approver
  Identifier:myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/1e4310262889ebdf72b8a7b148acdf2a
  Approved at:Mon Jul 09 16:21:47 CDT 2012
  Is approved? true
  approvals >

Another option is the flag -la which will print all the details of every item it applies to. For instance, to get a dump of every approval record in detail issue

        approvals>ls -la
    

The output is extremely lengthy however it is an easy way to get a text dump of a store. This flag has no effect if it is given for a specific id. All that will happen is that details of that id will be printed in full.

Updating (aka Editing) Objects.

This will let you update or edit an existing object. The general function is shown below. Current object values are shown in [ ]'s and simply hitting return will preserve the current value.
Example. Edit a client record. In this case we want to make this client use limited proxies.

    oa4mp >use clients
      clients >update /myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/6eb6ef83dbb89e7212cde073c7e682a4
      Update the values. A return accepts the existing or default value in []'s
        enter the identifier[myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/6eb6ef83dbb89e7212cde073c7e682a4]:
        enter the name[Another Ashigaru Gateway]:
        enter email[jgaynor@ncsa.illinois.edu]:
        enter error uri[http://ashigaru.ncsa.uiuc.edu:44444/client]:
        enter home uri[http://ashigaru.ncsa.uiuc.edu:44444/client]:

Up to this point we have changed nothing and have hit return each time. Now we change the value:

        does this client require limited proxies?[n]:y
        enter full path and file name of public key[-----BEGIN PUBLIC KEY----...]:
         public key entry skipped.

That finishes the entry for the client. Had we wanted to change the public key, we would have supplied a a file with complete path containing it. The system then prints out the entire new object and prompts us to save it:

        here is the complete client:
    Client name=Another Ashigaru Gateway
        identifier=myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/6eb6ef83dbb89e7212cde073c7e682a4
        email=jgaynor@ncsa.illinois.edu
        home uri=http://ashigaru.ncsa.uiuc.edu:44444/client
        error uri=http://ashigaru.ncsa.uiuc.edu:44444/client
        limited proxies? true
        creation timestamp=Thu Jun 28 13:46:31 CDT 2012
        approved by auto-approver
        public key:
      -----BEGIN PUBLIC KEY-----
    MIIBIjANBgkqhkiG9w0BAQEFAAOCAQ8AMIIBCgKCAQEAruhBa7EAnm8zDeBhNmuhYLUcij5pSr5r
    Z6481lhzvs0k+EtCsuDpr4RlcxUlX90uxF7ZsCjMSnk8pPr4e5HPu9lqr3wUb1TJbPbg3hdj/06O
    sJrOUYddVG5SmkafsCMmn+i5SrYq9vuWRsYVXZM36p/BzBzn4s4r6JqFzRWX71U9YybVCR72AIGi
    LClW2utUP3Q6axpDgkEXl6CuloGDshr1cMpct2/cpDqj6kpv5oV3WFUDiXf33kwqmBWjmXwCMTSu
    wAVhUmJNZ48YdnTQcotMURo9j5a1DBk1t2hKj/W7HqwT+TxnLgDu/cVxX5ZJDNTlgMaTbZKOFUhA
    MMnssQIDAQAB
    -----END PUBLIC KEY-----

        save [y/n]?y
        client updated.

Creating a new object

To create a new object, you must supply a unique identifier. This does not need to be escaped with a /. Once created, you will be given the option of editing it. You may enter any valid identifier as long as it is a valid URI
Example. Crreating a new client. This will create a new client with a specified identifier. If no identifier were supplied a random one would have been created.

    clients >create my:new:client
    Created object with id "my:new:client"

The object already exists in the store by this point. We will be given the option to edit it (equivalent to issuing the update command against its unique id):

      edit [y/n]?y
    Update the values. A return accepts the existing or default value in []'s
      enter the identifier[my:new:client]:
      enter the name[(null)]:My new client
      enter email[(null)]:foo@bar.baz
      enter error uri[(null)]:http://localhost/error
      enter home uri[(null)]:https:/localhost/home
      does this client require limited proxies?[n]:n
      enter full path and file name of public key[(null)]:
      No file entered. Public key entry skipped

Now the completed, new client is displayed and we are prompted if we want to keep the changes.

      here is the complete client:
    Client name=My new client
      identifier=my:new:client
      email=foo@bar.baz
      home uri=https:/localhost/home
      error uri=http://localhost/error
      limited proxies? false
      creation timestamp=Wed Nov 20 11:54:55 CST 2013
      no approval record exists.
      public key:
      none
      save [y/n]?y
      client updated.

Removing Objects From the Store.

Removing an object. This will remove the object completely from the store. In the case of clients you do not need to remove the corresponding approval -- it will be done automatically. However, if you remove the approval record then the client is in effect unapproved until you re-approve it. To remove the client we create with id my:new:client would look like the next
Example. Removing an object by id

    clients >rm /my:new:client
      Removing approval record
      Done. Client approval with id = my:new:client has been removed from the store
      removing client record
    Done. object with id = my:new:client has been removed from the store

Note The remove command will happily remove objects by index, but remember that the indices of all other objects change, so best practice is to only remove by identifier.

Invoking the components.

Clients

Invoke as

oa4mp> use clients

Operations allowed in addition to the standard ones are

approve [index | /uniqueID]

This will prompt you for the information needed to make a new approval for the client with the given id.

Approvals

Invoke as

oa4mp> use approvals

There are no extra options beyond the standard ones, however, the create command takes the unique id of the client record you are going to approve. Once created, you may enter the approval information directly.

Copy

Invoke as

oa4mp>use copy

Supported operation is

cp source target [-verify] - copy source to target optionally verifying

This works over the entire store. It has a single command that will allow you to make a copy of one store (the source) that completely replaces another (the target). This is destructive, meaning that the every object in the target is deleted, so no merge takes place. If the -verify option is used then the two stores are compared once the copy has been completed. Note that this can be very time consuming for a large store! However, if there is any question it is at times very useful.

Overview

Welcome to OAuth for MyProxy! This is a delegation service for MyProxy. It allows clients to request certificates and users to securely authorize them using the OAuth delegation protocol. Current release is 3.0.

Prerequisites

Tomcat 7 or above. This will not work with Tomcat 6 or lower because of internal changes to Java. (In particular, the way JSP is handled.)
SSL should be configured and enabled. Either in Apache (if you are deploying Tomcat as pass through) or in Tomcat directly. Note that if you do enable SSL in tomcat, you must un-comment the security constraint block in the web.xml deployment descriptor after you deploy the war.
Java 1.8. Note: Open JDK is not supported. Only the Oracle/Sun JVM is supported. Note especially that Oracle/Sun Java 1.7 or earlier will not work. This is because of changes to their security APIs.
Some form of persistent storage. This may be a file system, MySQL or PostgreSQL.
Java mail. This must be configured regardless if notifications are set. Read here for details.
Maven 3.0 or above (if building from the source)
Possibly either the latest MySQL connector. Maria DB client or PostgreSQL jar. If you are using one of these systems for storage, install them by dropping them in $CATALINA_HOME/lib. OA4MP used to bundle these in the wars, but since their licences conflicted with those of some of our users, we decided to simply let you supply them. If you are just using file-based storage, then you don't need either of these.
Possibly JGlobus. If your server needs to issue limited proxies drop the most recent version of JGlobus jsse (at least 2.0.6) into $CATALINA_HOME/lib as well as, apparently JGlobus-Core (latest release seems to be 2.0.4) and the Bouncy Castle version that support these. Otherwise, you may omit this. Again, be sure you check for the version of Bouncy Castle that your version of JGlobus uses and use that as well. JGlobus-Core 2.0.4 includes Bouncy Castle classes.
(Optional) Apache 2, configured to work with Tomcat.

Getting and deploying from the war.

You may most easily a bare-bones version for testing by downloading the current reference war:

oauth-server-latest.war
(PGP signature)

Download this, read to configure the deployment, and deploy it to Tomcat. The war, as delivered, cannot be run.You must do some minimal configuration at least before deploying it.

Using the Maven Repository

Fortunately, OA4MP is hosted on the public Sonatype maven repository so that using the code simply requires you add the right dependencies. There is no need to configure any repositories. Generally it is suggested that you use the pre-compiled war.

Getting and building the source

If you need/want to customize the basic package, you would download the webapp module from source forge by issuing

svn export https://svn.code.sf.net/p/cilogon/code/tags/edu.uiuc.ncsa/myproxy-4.1-SNAPSHOT/oa4mp-webapp

which has the correct dependencies in it. Build it by issuing

mvn clean install

and you should end up with a deployable war.

Writing your own webapp.

If you decide to write your own webapp, you should use the following module:

    <dependency>
        <artifactId>oa4mp-server-oauth1</artifactId>
        <groupId>edu.uiuc.ncsa.myproxy</groupId>
        <version>4.1-SNAPSHOT</version>
    </dependency>

which will get the OAuth libraries and give you access to the configuration loader.

Deploying to Apache

If you need to deploy this to Apache, you need to add the following to the proxy_ajp.conf file (which, e.g., lives under /etc/httpd/conf.d in most unix distributions):

ProxyPass /oauth/initiate ajp://localhost:8009/oauth/initiate

ProxyPass /oauth/authorize ajp://localhost:8009/oauth/authorize

ProxyPass /oauth/token ajp://localhost:8009/oauth/token

ProxyPass /oauth/getcert ajp://localhost:8009/oauth/getcert

ProxyPass /oauth/register ajp://localhost:8009/oauth/register

These entries allow access to all parts of the process. Note: in the WEB-INF/web.xml file there is a section called security-constraint, which controls access to the webapp using Tomcat's SSL. This will conflict with access via Apache, so comment that section out if you are deploying to Apache. It is only needed in stand-alone Tomcat deployments.

Setting up persistent storage

File-based storage

You may store all information for the service in your local file system. It is important that you restrict access to it and back it up. Specifying the storage location in your configuration file is sufficient, since the system will detect if it exists and create anything it needs.

MySQL

In order to use MySQL for persistent storage, you must run the supplied script, mysql.sql to create all of the tables and users before your first use.

mysql -u username -p < /path/to/file/mysql.sql

(the username is an account (root, e.g.) which has sufficient privileges to create other users) which will prompt you for your password and run the file. If you do not accept the default account names, you must edit this file and replace all occurrences of them manually, as well as setting the passwords. This has to be done because of MySQL's very lousy support for variables. (Should you have to re-run the script, you should manually remove the users and database beforehand. These commands are commented out at the beginning of the file.)

PostgreSQL

Most Unix distros have this database installed by default. There is a specific script, pg.sql, that will create all the tables. All you should need to do is set the passwords near the top of the file. Then you would need to log in to the command line psql tool as the user postgres (this is the super user) and from that prompt issue

\i /path/to/file/pg.sql

The file contains default user, table, database and schema names, which you may change if you see fit (be sure to pass these along in your configuration file!). Again, you only need to edit the values at the top of the file, thanks to PostgreSQL's support for variables.

Overview

After installing an OA4MP server, or as part of testing one in service, you may want to have a way to monitor the interaction from the command line. There are two ways to do this, either using the custom command line client or using curl. This document is how to test using curl. This is not quite straightforward and does require some work, but in many cases is well worth the effort. This document describes how to do a complete exchange with a properly configured OA4MP server

Prerequisites

You should make sure you have a few things at the ready.

A valid, registered client and its ID
The client should not be running, or the client does not exist, meaning that you register a client and use a valid but bogus callback uri. If the callback uri is valid, the server will try to contact it, as per the spec.
A url encoder or decoder. I like this one.
A valid certification request. You can create on using openssl, or you can invoke
Access to the server from the command line. Depending upon your setup this may require you to be logged in to the server and send everything to localhost.

The steps

Each of the steps is outlined below along with an example curl call. In each call you will need to supply your own client_id, client_secret and redirect_uri. Other values such as the nonce and state may be left as is.

Step 1: The authorization page

In this case, you will create a custom url that you will paste into your browser. Line breaks are for readability.

    https://surge.ncsa.illinois.edu/oauth2/authorize?
    client_id=myproxy%3Aoa4mp%2C2012%3A%2Fclient_id%2F2a3aab4b67ab2354563&
    redirect_uri=https%3A%2F%2Fashigaru.ncsa.uiuc.edu%3A9443%2Fclient%2Fready&
    state=qqqqq&
    response_type=code&
    scope=openid+edu.uiuc.ncsa.myproxy.getcert&
    nonce=n-0S6_WzA2Mj

Step 2: Get authorized.

At this point you should see the authorization page pop up in your browser. Log in. The normal control flow is to call back to the redirect URL you provided in the previous step. Since no client should be running there, you will get an error.

Step 3: Grab the authorization grant (aka code) from the browser location bar.

The location bar will have an address like this in it

    https://ashigaru.ncsa.uiuc.edu:9443/client/ready?
    code=https%3A%2F%2Fsurge.ncsa.illinois.edu%2Foauth2%2FauthzGrant%2F6d08e01649cb7d766b0c6288333377b1%2F1453837119100&
    state=qqqqq

Note that the state passed in initially is returned. You can ignore this. The important thing is the code. This must be swapped out for a access token.

Step 4:Getting an access token.

This requires a little more work since you have to do a POST (as per the spec) using cURL. In this example, I am using the -k flag to avoid checking the SSL cert for the server. This may or may not be required for your setup and the -d parameter that gloms together the request, allowing it to be entered on multiple lines:

    curl -k --location -d code=https%3A%2F%2Fsurge.ncsa.illinois.edu%2Foauth2%2FauthzGrant%2F6d08e01649cb7d766b0c6288333377b1%2F1453837119100 \
    -d client_id=myproxy%3Aoa4mp%2C2012%3A%2Fclient_id%2F2a3aab4b67ab2354563 \
    -d client_secret=KYuXckx3yilsiwl6Z3934587KSUIF983489_3498drfgn3 \
    -d redirect_uri=https%3A%2F%2Fashigaru.ncsa.uiuc.edu%3A9443%2Fclient%2Fready \
    -d grant_type=authorization_code \
    https://surge.ncsa.illinois.edu/oauth2/token

Note that the actual endpoint goes at the end of this request. You should get a response like this:

    {"access_token":"https://surge.ncsa.illinois.edu/oauth2/accessToken/20c290985f42bf8efb0677b8db67971e/1453837731113",
    "refresh_token":"https://surge.ncsa.illinois.edu/oauth2/refreshToken/49e7fd57565264e2710ddec6d266f84a/1453837731113",
    "id_token":"eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJub25lIn0.eyJpc3MiOiJodHRwcz.",
    "token_type":"Bearer",
    "expires_in":900}

Again, you just need the access_token.

Step 5: Use your cert request.

It is assumed you generated a cert request before you started. In that case, you need to URLencode the cert request you created and send it along in the request (which is just a GET).

    curl -k --location
    "https://surge.ncsa.illinois.edu/oauth2/getcert?
    access_token=https%3A%2F%2Fsurge.ncsa.illinois.edu%2Foauth2%2FaccessToken%2F20c290985f42bf8efb0677b8db67971e%2F1453837731113&
    client_id=myproxy%3Aoa4mp%2C2012%3A%2Fclient_id%2F2a3aab4b67ab2354563&
    client_secret=KYuXckx3yilsiwl6Z3934587KSUIF983489_3498drfgn3&
    certreq=MIICfzCCAWcCAQAwOjEMMAoGA1UEBhMDVVNBMQswCQYDVQQKEwJPVTELMAkGA12B7lBCgs6hf73A%3D%3D"

The response is just the certificate.

    -----BEGIN CERTIFICATE-----
    MIIEOzCCAyOgAwIBAgIDXB6BMA0GCSqGSIb3DQEBCwUAMIGDMQswCQYDVQQGEwJVUzE4MDYGA1UE
    ChMvTmF0aW9uYWwgQ2VudGVyIGZvciBTdXBlcmNvbXB1dEb...
    ...

Writing your own loader

In some cases you might want to extend the functionality of OA4MP. For instance, writing your own storage for transactions or username transformer. This involves a few relatively simple steps, which are imposed on us by Tomcat's architecture.

Setup your maven project.

You need to check out oa4mp-webapp from svn. This has everything in it you need.

Write your extension.

In the src/main/java folder you should create the package you want and put the class. Most major components of OA4MP are defined as interfaces (such as storage, username transformations) and can be simply implemented.

Extend OA4MPConfigurationLoader.

Specifically, you want to override the method (getter) that returns an instance of your new class. This is where the class is instantiated. Note that there will be one copy of this class available at all times, so you should plan to not store state between calls.

Extend AbstractBootstrapper

Specify Your abstract bootstrapper in web.xml

Build your war